Guide to the Henry James Seibert Papers, 1779-1912 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Henry James Seibert papers 1779-1912 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Seibert, Henry James
Extent: 16,658 Items
Lawyer, election clerk, and Virginia legislator, of Martinsburg and Hedgesville, Virginia (now West Virginia). Correspondence, account books, ledgers, and other professional, business, and family correspondence (chiefly 1820-1885), of Seibert and of his family. The collection relates to family matters, Virginia and national politics before the Civil War, migration into the Old Northwest, social life and customs, and slavery in Virginia.
seiberthenryjames
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Henry James Seibert Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1948-1952.
Collection Overview
Spanning the years 1779-1912, the collection contains correspondence, legal and financial papers, and printed material of Henry James Seibert, Sr., Virginia state legislator, executor for numerous estates, and financial agent for emigrants to the Mid-West.
The correspondence discusses personal and family matters; internal improvements in Pennsylvania during the 1820s; salt mining in Pennsylvania; commodity and land prices in Ohio during the 1820s and 1830s; Ohio politics during the 1830s and the attitude of politicians towards the Second Bank of the United States; commodity prices in Illinois during 1838 and 1840; bank failures in Ohio, 1841; wages in Ohio, 1845; care of a ward of Henry James Seibert, Sr., in an insane asylum; the National Road in Ohio; presidential elections of 1840, 1844, 1848, 1852, and 1856; the National Democratic Convention of 1844; Henry Clay and the Whig Party; the slavery question in relation to the California Territory; improvement and construction of public buildings in Washington, D.C.; coal mining in Maryland; the Compromise of 1850; cholera in New Orleans, 1850s; internal improvements in Virginia, 1850s; control and sale of liquor and distillation of whiskey; slave trade in the United States; Civil War bounty; pension claims; and other matters.
Also included are bills and receipts; indentures; court summonses; account sheets; applications for pensions; prospectus, 1865, of The New Era, a newspaper to be published in Martinsburg, West Virginia; bulletin of Wellesley College, Wellesley, Massachusetts, for 1879; pamphlets containing West Virginia laws in 1887 relating to public schools; advertisements for the Maryland Lottery Company, the Kentucky State Lottery, cooking and heating stoves, women's fashions for 1884-1885, and patent medicines; Reformed Missionary Herald, 1889; almanacs; price current sheets for Baltimore, Maryland, in 1867 and 1869; premium list of the annual fair of the Ogle County (Illinois) Agricultural Board in 1881; ballots for the Greenback Party, the Democratic Party in Berkeley County (West Virginia) in 1880 and 1888, and the National Prohibition Party in 1884; pamphlet of the National Prohibition Party; form letter, 1849, explaining the stand of the Society of Friends of Great Britain and Ireland on slavery; broadsides of a U.S. pension agency; and announcement and program of the 29th annual session of the Farmers' National Congress, Raleigh, 1909.
There are also many 19th century manuscript volumes - daybooks, ledgers, and account books - containing financial records of the general mercantile establishments of John W. Boyd and Benjamin R. Boyd; Hezekiah Hedges; Henry J. Seibert; and of William L. Seibert.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Land settlement -- Northwest, Old; Migration, Internal -- United States; Slavery -- Virginia; Merchants -- Virginia; Northwest, Old -- Emigration and immigration; United States -- Politics and government -- 1783-1865; Virginia -- Economic conditions; Virginia -- Politics and government -- 1775-1865; Virginia -- Social life and customs
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1819-1912 and undated, (7 boxes)
  - 1819-1844 (Box 1)
  - 1845-1849 (Box 2)
  - 1850-1853 (Box 3)
  - 1854-1865 (Box 4)
  - 1866-1872 (Box 5)
  - 1873-1880 (Box 6)
  - 1881-1912 and undated (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous Papers Series, 1879-1889 and undated, (3 boxes)
  - 1852-1875 (Box 8)
  - 1879-1889 (Box 9)
  - undated (Box 10)
- Financial Papers Series, 1779-1900s and undated, (23 boxes)
  - Bills and Receipts (Box 11)
    - 1779-1819
    - 1820s (Box 12)
    - 1820s (Box 13-15)
    - 1830s (Box 16-22)
    - 1840s (Box 23-27)
    - 1850s (Box 28-30)
    - 1850s, 1870s-1890s (Box 31)
    - 1900s and undated (Box 32)
    - undated (Box 33)
- Mercantile Manuscript Volumes Series
  Dozens of manuscript volumes are included in this collection. For location see the online catalog record.